so how can one or how should one train
oneself to become unaffected by harsh
speech or by evil actions done by others
towards himself
aimed at oneself yeah like people are
insulting you how do you make the
suitors were quite clear on it you you
wouldn't do the harsh speech the insults
in the same manner you wouldn't do the
elements in the same manner you wouldn't
your wind rain heat of cold
bites of insects you also endure the
harsh words so it's really a no-brainer
in the sense of you need to really
figure it out just comes down to being
able to endure it without resorting to
what will will yourself and the only
reason people cannot endure it it's
because the habit of acting out of it
it's just too established and they keep
maintaining it so in order to break that
habit of acting out of ill will in order
to break the habit of acting out of
ill-will you just need to stop acting
out of your will and endure that
unpleasant feeling that's it arises when
somebody attacks you verbally or because
no amount of things said at you can
actually harm you it's your not being
able to keep the mind away from it you
not being able to withstand things that
are said at you you jump into it and
that's why you suffer that's why you get
affected by it
to people when people get offended
nobody denies the the offensive words
but you becoming offended that's a new
that's on your own inability to keep
your mind out of it
as the Buddha said in that simile when
he was walking in the park
and a man came in front of a man's house
and he started shouting abuse at him
this man and then as the Buddha was
walking away he turned to the man and
said well let me ask you something if
you have guests come to you don't come
to your home and you give them gifts and
but they don't take them who do those
gifts stay for any man said well of
course I stay for me my gifts you didn't
take them they stay for me so well so
it's with your insults and your harsh
words I'm not taking them so it just
stays with you and it's not just it's
not just just a poetic kind of poetic
put-down it's it's genuine
phenomenologically that's what happens
if the mind does not respond with
ill-will to your will the only
experience with
ill-will that's left is the experience
of the man so he's the only one left
with anger but if the Buddha did give it
to anger and then replied something or
put him in his place out of anger and so
on well then there would have been an
engagement and they would feel further
and then the man would have not but he
just by not responding to it but being
able to take it without being actually
affected by it it highlighted that no
amount of abuse can actually step
outside of that man's experience so he
he was the only one left with that
painful anger nobody else that's that
suitor that you are talking about ha ha
got a little X excerpt from it oh I'll
just read it shortly
he says the Buddha says whoever returns
insult to one who is insulting returns
taunt to one who is taunting returns a
berating to one who is berating is said
to be eating together sharing company
with that person but I am neither eating
together nor sharing your company drums
all yours it's all yours where is it
but okay yeah yeah that's the one I was
thinking of so what I might have another
suitor as well I'll come too that's
forbearance patience with a person who
is getting angry at you that is said to
be the foremost good the former's good
for you the former's good for that
person but others would say well if you
just you don't react you don't respond
to that person you don't fight back then
that person just and you just stay
patient and calm and act like a weak
weak person in front of that president
you're just gonna attack you even more
it's gonna just chase you so you should
fight back you should with this that
comes out of an out of a confusion
between what weakness is you weak when
you're mentally affected by someone's
anger as there is usually in practical
terms and somebody's affected mentally
that's when they start acting bodily to
defend themselves and that's how you
show your weakness by being effective
mentally now people who think that all you must
now people who think that all you must
do something in return
otherwise you'll be perceived weak they
confuse doing something in return with
with being effective mentally because if
you're not effective mentally and you
don't do anything in return the other
person will see them they will see that
you are not bullied mentally despite not
fighting back physically they did they
can't break the mind literally that's on
you you give in to that
or not
but then so in other words you cannot
return it physically without being
affected mentally but you can remain
unaffected mentally and not to do
anything physically doing something
physically in return requires you to be
affected mentally now in order to not be
able to in order to not be affected
mentally you first need to stop
entertaining the habit of doing
something physically that requires
mental mental effect as well underneath
so once you stop acting physically then
you highlight for yourself the fact that
the problem is not you or should have
done this too sure than that no all I
should have done is not allow myself to
be affected mentally and then whatever
you do it will define how do you not
have you how he not mentally affected
well you can reflect how would it be to
endure your elements and you the heat or
cold if you don't know well expose
yourself to it a bit just don't don't
don't pursue comfort physical comfort
all the time in your life experience
some discomfort and then see how my mind
rebels against it I want to do I want to
make you I want to get rid of it it's
the same attitude towards harsh speech
whether it's random insults but you
can't really go and try and find hard
well you don't have to really go and
find it I mean you just need to he's
gonna come to you sooner or later but in
that sense yeah well you can't go and
find this physical discomfort the mind
doesn't want to endure it doesn't want
to deal with and by training in regard
to that your training in regard to the
mental discomfort as well and then when
the harsh speech does come while you're
already trained from no not not reacting
some people can endure you know the
elements extreme elements push
themselves to the limit but when it
comes when someone challenges their
views on the rationality or whatever
believe or God doesn't exist well that's
why it's not like you can't just go and
do your elements and expect wisdom to
come out of it you need to know what
you're supposed to look for so that's
why I'm saying if you know what your
support if you know that the nature of
being insulted being challenged like on
no particular ground
just gratuitous installer offense that
equals enduring the elements but if you
don't know that you won't look for that
when you enjoy the elements which means
then you won't be trained in regard to
it there's something to do with taking
things personally oh absolutely yes
whether the element well feeling feeling
like like feeling entitled to to break
away from discomfort for example in
physical terms or taking things
personally when somebody verbally says
something to you that you don't like you
can't help but take it personally well
you can't help but you haven't been
training yourself to help so now the
habit is just take it personal and then
just lash out because you deserves it
and I mean people can take that so far
when you know when you get the outrage
culture like in Europe for example and
they witness obviously it's just people
get outraged furious over things that
doesn't don't even concern it now that
doesn't mean or shouldn't do anything
about rectifying wrong but you shouldn't
get angry on account of random wrong
that's not the rectifying the wrong can
be done without the anger but if you're
acting out of anger then the purpose of
your action is just acting our Wanga no
amount of lofty goal cannot prove that
anger and make it whole song by the way
is there enough light I'm not too dark
on the screen
it's getting a bit darker okay
so what is what is the correct response
then to an aggressive the person
physically aggressive verbally recipe yeah
well I mean if your life is physically
threatened again you don't have to
obviously you know we're not I'm not he
killing or harming but if you can subdue
the person to give yourself enough room
to escape that's fine if you can just
escape that's even better
but when it comes to verbally aggressive
again say the first the main response is
to not respond and then recognize well
there is no communication here obviously
so you don't try to change your mind so
you just remove yourself from that
situation how about the simile of the
soul put it gay you know
yeah that's when you can't escape yeah
that's what you cannot escape when they
catch you and start showing you're
limping well even then you can be similar of the
well even then you can be similar of the
soul and highway robbers
so you limb by limb savagely again
doesn't mean you don't feel any pain but
the other hand to the alighted person
one who is fulfill the Buddhist teaching
he doesn't feel anger towards them on
account of such extreme action and there
is something you should train for people
will dismiss that or that's a tall order
well if you don't aim for a tall order
how can you expect to arrive at anything
if you made a compromise before you even
started practicing so just contemplate
how would it be how would you feel if
somebody physically attacks you like
life-threatening attack and you can't
get away you can't get away and you
can't defend yourself they're more
greater in number stronger than you how
would you feel would your mind be
overwhelmed by that experience if so
there is a work for you you don't need
to go and seek out the danger you just
think about it and it will it will it
will bring the experience so it's
efficiently enough to be able to
contemplate who does let us say that pervading the
who does let us say that pervading the
world with kindness you know once you
train in pervading the world with
kindness the waiting the world
parading the your experience of the
world with non your will
which is what kindness is not like
aiming at person individually or I love
you I love you if I love you to know
pervading would kindness means being
incapable of ill-will towards the
framework on the basis of which
experience of others manifests so if
your mind has discerned the phenomenon
of ill-will and anger and stopped
entertaining it no amount of people or
circumstances coming your way with anger
will be able to provoke you angry that
means your mind is above anger whatever
you do then it will be kind as in it
will be not based in your will just say
someone has already found you huh so
you've been harmed in the past well what
has been harmed in the past that's the
thing I mean well what what part of me
what cannot a person related when they
relate with you what can they see what
can they aim at what can be harm or not
harm my body exactly so the body that
you are paired with has been harmed but
you can't help but take it personally so
thus I am I was harmed but that's a new
you don't have to not being body being
harmed is not a new but you taking that
body which can be harmed or was harmed
or could be on that's a new so you take
that it doesn't belong to you and
because of that you make yourself liable
to harm and again it comes from the self
entitlement that we all have obviously
especially when you you know you just
live a normal life without any effort
of your mind yeah you think you have
every right to pleasure to sense
pleasures every right to to pursuit of
satisfaction many have every right to
avoid pain that's only true in a
relative sense because fundamentally you
don't have right to that which can
experience pleasure or experience pain
namely your senses
they were then on yours you paid with
their given to bother them yet you act
like you the master and then when they
don't go your way
yeah your mastery you the core of your
very being is very compromising and
that's very unpleasant so that's how you
forgive the past insults or harm done to
you you realize that it cannot be done
to you as in to your point of view to
your experience as a whole it can only
be done to one aspect of it that others
can perceive and relate to did you do
that you don't need to take personal so
you're saying that is the that is the
what it sound always what it sounds like
that is the only cure truly yeah that's
a true forgiveness yeah
what overcoming overcoming future
liability overcoming present there is a
thing safety food get there that's the
thing if you if the Dhamma is applied
correctly you don't have to I mean
obviously to do it repetitively as in
training training yourself and develop
it but if he's developed rightly it
affects present and past through present
and future through that present as a
Buddhist everyone who understands that
not self not myself he understands that
has their insight
he's also he also understands the past
so he stops thinking oh I was in the
past now I'm not anymore or I will not
be in the future I will be in the future
know that the whole domain of temporal
existence is uprooted by this
understanding whether it was the past
future present it's not mine
it could it could have not been mine
so your Venge is not an option
no absolutely because revenge engaging
the revenge means engaging upon the act
that's fully founded in the perversion
of that principle of not mine
which means you took it as mine which
means in try it implies revenge
retaliation saying back with with
ill-will it implies that taking up his
mind taking up as I can I can act upon
this and then how can you undo it if you
keep acting wrongly out of it and you
maintain that the wrong god
so there's the
most common questions for the human
being why am I here you know how did
this universe begin who created the
world what is the purpose my meaning of
life what's going on where am I going
where I come from but then if you read
the suitors those questions are wrong
why they run why are they wrong question
things because they come out of that
that mistake of assuming the ownership
mastery assuming the the master self of
the experience they come out of that
wrong order that was just talking about
so where did I come from what is my
purpose it's all based on that self
center or the center itself and as such
providing any answer just affirms the
wrong order you know if somebody comes
with the wrong premise and ask your
question whereby if you answer it will
you give the validity to the premise
that they've wrongly assumed as a basis
of the question so that's why the Buddha
just wouldn't answer or he would say he
would give the petition father he would
say with the rising of this this arises
with the rising of ignorance
determinations manifest and so on how
does that relate well exactly relates to
directly explaining you were not
explaining directly describing you that
principle of perversion of a potential
butter with the grain or but it's and
butter against the grain which is
developed properly and that would undo
that wrong order simultaneous the
present wrong order of you taking that
which is not yours as mine and then
those questions would cease they will be
meaning what questions would you have instead
what questions would you have instead
why do I suffer how can i free myself
from suffering
am I really a master of my experience in
control of my life can I not get sick
can I not be aging can I make sure my
heart never stops can I not get cancer
can I not die
that's important yeah well fundamentally
just keep asking yourself in regard to
whatever you do just keep asking so why
do I want to do this why am I asking
this question even then why am i asking
myself this because the world the senses
pull you out they directly art they
entice you out with pleasures and so on
asking these questions would keep sort
of pointing back inwards but not in some
sort of mystifying sense but in a sense
of looking for answers
so with questions like what happens
after death again body dies any notion
of death that you can have is based on
this life thus it's not really death
that which death is so then you're
asking question based on what you think
death is what happens after it well it's
it's doubly meaningless same trying to
understand how the workings of the comma
and the Parker and the G's and whatnot
as the Buddha said that just on a result
result in destruction or madness
you can't fathom it cuz you don't need
to
how does samsara operates
but instead ask yourself why do I want
to know that why do I seek this form of
knowledge why do I need that information
what for
what's the what's the motivation behind
and you see the motivation behind every
single action you ever done you ever you
will ever do and you're doing is
motivated in how you feel of how you
want to feel always okay so what if I
overcome two feelings then there's
nothing for me to do anymore so for
example someone's looking for I want to
find out if there is a God if God
created right that's my mission right so
you're saying then ask yourself why is
that why did you make that a mission of
yours because if I find out that there
is a God what's gonna happen I'll feel
great after sex Ralphy ladies off you
will feel pleasant
so then you you realize it that if you
want to do something your actions should
be aimed at understanding the motivation
for you wanted to do things in the first
place as an understanding motivation for your
as an understanding motivation for your
feeling being the reason for your action
feelings being the receiver
so tell if people want to know what is
the harlot the world's begin how did the
universe begin the only reason I want to
know that is because they think that
that answer will provide a satisfaction
which is a form of pleasure but on a
level of a view almost so then they have
a view that then they can apply
throughout their life as everything will
be fine
that's what people want to have the goal
exists in the heaven and stuff just to
provide that utterly at most general
pleasure then they can use to sort of go
go through life without fear and anxiety
but what they fail to see because it's
very unpleasant to see it is that that
pleasure is still based on this life
thus you don't really you cannot really
know anything different from it so you
cannot really know oh yes there is
heaven after or there is god that there
isn't God because you're full enclosed
within yourself and within your own
experience and that's that that honesty
that's necessary to recognize that
actually certain things cannot be known
based on this experience you cannot know
how it would be to be outside of this
experience and even when you think about
outside of this experience that's within
your experience so then all the views
that you hold on account of it - like
reinterpret the life back to yourself
which is a form of regaining the control
this is how the universe started this is
how the universe will end this is heaven
this is hell it's just the form of
greater control over that which you know
deep down you're not not in control of
and that's why you're liable to feelings
feelings of fear and unpleasantness and
so on
to the piece like science you know
looking into a tonight sorry
science looking into small accent right
looking into distant horizon measuring
the universe yeah I can bring benefit
well they can be bring benefit in terms
of information about the world about
about about the matter of your
experience but not not information about
the tools you use to gather information
which is the tools of your senses your
mind your thoughts your intention ality
your feelings your views you can't read
open them through things that you
discover based on them they're secondary
to it that's why the Buddha said you
won't reach the universe by traveling to
the end of the world or something you
the beginning and the end of universe is
in this very body nowhere else that's it
this very experience as a whole that's
your entire universe and no matter no
matter how far you go in the universe
imagine could you go without this body
being there present you couldn't could
you even imagine it abstractly without
this body being still alive here you
could know you're fully enclosed in it
and that's the point that it's useful to
contemplate it's not like you bound with
it as in you're tied to a post and then
you can move around a post no you have
within it the body's the container the
senses of your container the five
aggregates are the container that you
cannot conceive the outside of that's
what the Buddha said even people in
meditation who would develop memory of
the previous life one previous life five
previous lives 500 previous lives all
they would remember is these five
aggregates or one among them you can't
step outside of an elephant doesn't step
outside of it he removes the slightest
trace of ownership in regard to that
experience as a whole slightest trace of
ownership in regard to feelings in
regard to matter feeling perception
intentions and and unconsciousness
and that's how he disappears so to speak
frees himself from it
you have any direct method to
I've become this sense of ownership
contemplate through your ownership that
which you own so take a bet which you
regard as yours and then see how or
rather where it is routed at whether in
your sense of control or whether it's
something else that it is in yours so
for example the body take up the body my
body is that sense of my body is that
the center of it Oh would this body be
depending upon all these individual
organs within that sense of ownership of
this body that that are required to be
operating that I cannot control
if those organs would fail would I be
able to entertain the notion of this
body's mind if this body dies right
right in front of me sirs you realize EU
couldn't so you you're perverting the
order by regarding by giving the
priority of their sense of self of my
master of this body and then when you
think about the individual organs you
don't think about them within that sense
of Master you think of our left right
before or after that's where you don't
approach it so the closest or method
would be to contemplate within this
ownership so you can't leave the
ownership out and contemplate things
right because the whole point of
contemplation is to experience the non
ownership and you experience the non
ownership when you see that this body no
matter how much it's in your control its
heart is rooted in that which you cannot
even conceive controlling such as heart
breathing lungs pumping blood operating
organs functioning brain
you can't even conceive how it would be
to control those things who have saying
they're operating yet
they are the fundamental basis for the
notion of your body as a whole that you
do on the estate we really think we come
we myself comes first
yes I come first us this is for me this
is mine it's other way around it's
because I take all this to be mine I
develop a sense of I am but that sense
of I am can be undone nobody's denying
the best thing are there's no self they
don't really me look everything is
changing this is numb no you need to
take up that sense of I am and then see
that it's founded upon things that
cannot be yours then automatically your
experience is the experience of not I am
reversing the mistake yeah draining
basically draining and that the kind of
the structure stays the same but what
has drained away is that appropriation
from it that's how the Buddha would say
foreign our hands like a palm stump cut
at its root so the stump the branches
that grown this state but now they then
done they're petrified they're still
there as the way persons experience my
proliferate throughout the ignorant life but once
throughout the ignorant life but once
you approve that ignorance once you
remove that appropriation it stops
proliferating and then just stays like a
palm stamp until even that breaks apart
in part in a bond so if you lose it or
get rid of its sense of ownership your
personality doesn't how does your
personality well anything in your
personality that was depending upon the
ownership that will disappear but there
are the things that were not depending
upon ownership they were depending upon
like holo habits habits they were not
rooted in greed aversion delusion that
stays that's why as I said many times
and in the sutras you read off the
people cannot tell another hunt external
and even another our hunt can opt come
and see the light on it's a special
order around we can tell in our hand
when they start discussing each other's
understanding of Dhamma and they can see
oh yeah he understood this probably to
the extent of course then the Buddha or
somebody with very very developed mind
could see little traits little things
based on which he could tell the other
person's mind but on an average you
can't even like sorry puta couldn't tell
in some cases that the person was
another hand then we go to the Buddha
and said where was his rebirth and says
what you mean didn't he say he was
another yeah he did but he was
associating with some not some reputable
families and so he said well that's
that's not my person he's blamed world a
person claimed body because they leave
this body they take another body as in
they keep to remain bound with samsara
but I can tell you he wasn't he wasn't
blame water he was another thing even
before he died but so pretty cool to see
so the or the other that that famous one
was like really harsh in his speech and
the people were often offended and then
the Buddha said oh it's his old habits
they they were not rooted in ill-will or
greed or anything like that but
obviously people come across as very
angry furious
of course that doesn't mean they are
okay so I don't have to you will know
that you will know which habits can stay
once you're in our hand or on the way of
becoming one you can't decide that
beforehand no these are my neutral
habits so you have to take them all with
caution if you're in a state of Utah
Jeana you can't trust any of your habits
so you have to keep investigating any of
it if it's rooted on greed aversion
delusion and truly truly when you
dismantle everything that shouldn't be
there whatever so that then you know
that can be left so it's very different
from saying that the self doesn't exist
the Buddha never said them but he asked
you does the self exist he would have
said as itself does not exist he
wouldn't answer it no it's a it's a
shortcut it's a quick fix in terms of
experts Attis fiying explanation but
it's not a contemplation when you say
there's no self look all these rocks
they're constantly changing electrons
and atoms that's nothing is real does
there is no self this is just the whole
of convention conventional speech and so
on no that's that's not what a good
asset because you can because inventions
are real as such yeah you might not call
it self but the thing is that phenomena
that you refer to yourself it's there if
they weren't there you wouldn't be able
to refer to it whatsoever
so this missing the reality does not
remove your ownership of that reality
which means ah so I should be concerned
with me appropriating reality not being
concerned about dismantling conventions
improving the that nothing exists
because that's like instead of treating
the illness in regard to the Bobby you
just go and chop up the body and say see
the body can be chopped up thus it's not
real no it is real as as a collection of
parts that can be chopped up that's a
reality and there was never a problem
so there is that self there is that
sense of self it's not that there is no
self but what you should do is remove
the ownership of that sense of self and
then it becomes anata as in not my self
because it practice of denial and
actually I want to say not myself
because when people might assume or
someone else itself know anata is self
that you don't own and they cannot be
called itself so it's not self so that
which was taken itself still there but
now it's not taken is not itself but
people are concerned with denying that
which is taking itself which is an
aspect of their experience one way or
the other but as the Buddha said the
five aggregates are not the assumption
are not the holding the view of the self
but there is no view of the self apart
from the five argument to desire and
lust in regard to the 500 the view of
self is there by you coming and saying
there's no self the Pirates are
impermanent there is no self you're just
dismissing it the problem and without
actually understanding it because if you
were to if you were to truly understand
it well the only way to truly understand
it is to feel yourself from that self to
see it is not self so an explanation
that you think understood unless it's
freeing you from that sense itself don't
think you understood it because people
can put a lot of time and effort in
denial yeah many of the meditation
methods and techniques are all based on
that view just denial and seeing the
moment-to-moment movement they were kind
of show you that somehow things are not
really real cannot be yours but that
that whole practice goes completely
against being self transparent honest
authentic yeah saying this I do
experience this there is mother there is
father there is there's no gender yeah
well okay people can deny anything
whatever they please as their teacher
there can be a literally at anything
that's why the Buddha said the right the
worldly right view is the view that
acknowledges the validity of random
phenomena of phenomena and your
experience now there is this there is
there is given there is they there is
mother there is father there is the
liberation there is a part allowing them
like you don't need to see them or when
of course you don't see them at that
level but you need to know that there is
a possibility of them being
being real as in there is a possibility
of being free but if you keep denying
everything you will never accept that
possibility as a present phenomenon and
that's the key accepting possibilities
as a present negative phenomenon your
experience yeah it's real the
possibility is real I don't know how to
our extent but I could find out if I
apply myself so you don't want to deny
anything really you want to restrain
yourself from what you were told it's
unwholesome greed evil delusion that you
can see that it's an awesome and then
within that you don't need to deny
further there will be like overshooting
the mark you want to understand what's
in front you that's what we have said
the whole universe is contained within
this less than six foot long body so you
see this body is not real that's none of
the universe is real that's not there is
no travel there is no matter its own
father there's no life because there
were those views at the time that he
quite heavily criticized now nobody gets
killed there's nothing it's just
elements just and actually modern
interpretation of Buddha Sonata it's
actually one of those wrong views back
in the day that the Buddha criticized
when this everything is comprised of
constantly changing electrons among so
nothing is real or nothing nothing can
be mine there is no self and people
believe that whereby they said oh nobody
gets killed even if you go and cut
everybody on the left side of Ganges
with a sharp sword nobody gets killed
all that happens is the like the sword
runs through the elements runs through
the electrons and atoms you can just
call it whatever you want the view is
the same and it will say it's completely
wrong view because you blaming the five
aggregates for your assumption for your
sense of self failing to see that it's
desire and lust in regard to the five
agreed that the sense of self is there
but it's not the five aggregates so
you're killing the five aggregates does
not free you from the sense of self
hence person who is not freed from the
sense of self when the five aggregates
disintegrate as in when they die they're
still there they get reborn it reminds
me of when someone's got a problem in
assault you know complaining about
trying to talk it out
and then I don't know the answer but
anyway anyway everything is impermanent
so yeah anyway it's okay so it's like
this oh well oh I've got this problem
but I'll just deny it now no
unfortunately it's it's it's it's it's
prevalent as a view but it's it just
rooted in in lazy self-reflection I can
in self-reflection that doesn't go far
enough so then you just put a cap on it
to buy it right by saying ah well it's
all impermanent anyway so I won't bother
with it
I'll just didn't watch my breath to be
peaceful and live a simple life you can
live life is as simply as you want as a
vegetable and still remain equally
ignorant and that's the problem it's not
how complex your life is of course you
want to simplify it because can be too
much in I'd like to start with to
practice but that's secondary let's just
create in the suitable condition for you
to understand what's right in front of
me but thinking that the goal of your
life is to simplify or to just do this
just do that without making the effort
to understand it and go through that
unpleasant and so fun reveling the the
deep existential feelings of fear and
anxiety yeah there's no practice with
other